There was a famous leaked memo from
Google in May 23 and it says we have no
moat. And what they meant was the
intellectual property which will hold
something safe, which will keep
everybody off, allow you to charge
revenue. And I think that's going to be
the case with most things in AI. We've
ended up with eight companies who
control the digital infrastructure. And
I don't think anybody wants to see that
as the AI future with eight companies
controlling our AI future. So, the value
of open things up to something that is
much more understood now than it was
years ago when we began those big tech
journeys. If you talk to people today
about Lama and Meta, they'll say to you
that they're moving away from openness.
And I think it's because they haven't
done it right. The license has two
things. It has an acceptable use for
policy that puts restrictions in and it
has commercialization provision that
says when you hit X million users, you
have to go back and get a commercial
license from Meta. To get the real value
from open source, it goes way beyond
that legal definition of having a
license and making it open. It goes to
the heart of community and collaboration
and contribution.
>> Given that there are significant number
of open source options for people to
pick from, why are most developers still
defaulting to closed model APIs as their
go-to?
>> It's interesting. I think
>> Back in November, we hosted the first
ever in-person AI Native Dev Con in New
York. This June 1st and 2nd, we're
bringing it to London. It's two days
built for AI Native developers and
engineering teams. One day full of
hands-on workshops and one day full of
practical talks on agent skills, context
engineering, agent orchestration and
enablement platforms, and how teams are
actually shipping AI in production.
Join us at the brewery in London near
the Barbican for all of that plus
networking, parties, giveaways, and a
room full of people building the future
of AI native development. You can also
join us from anywhere in the world via
the live stream.
As you're listening to this podcast, you
get 30% off your ticket with code pod30.
Just head to ainativedevcon.io
and we'll see you in London.
On today's episode, we're going to be
talking about AI openness. What does an
open-source model actually mean? What
are open weights? And what is open
training data? And what do we in the
West need to learn from our Chinese
counterparts in order to not fall
further behind in our open-source
journey? Hello and welcome to another
episode of the AI Native Dev. And today
we're going to be talking about all
things open-source. Uh joining me today
is the CEO of OpenUK, Amanda Brock.
Amanda, welcome to the session. How are
you?
>> Thank you very much for having me along,
Simon.
>> It's an absolute
>> Finally.
>> It's an absolute pleasure. We've been
talking about this for quite some time
now. And uh either you're traveling, I'm
traveling, you're ill, I'm ill, but
finally we found a we found a day where
we could be here in person in London.
And you're of course UK-based. Um
OpenUK, tell us a little bit about
OpenUK cuz I think a lot of our
listeners will maybe have heard of
OpenUK from some of the reports and and
and research that has been created or
maybe State of Open Con in the UK, a
conference you run. But tell us a little
bit about what it is.
>> So, we're just over 6 years old at
OpenUK and we are an industry
organization with a difference. We
realized very quickly that the other
industry organizations in other
countries for open tech, so software,
hardware, data, standards, and AI,
that they focus on companies and by
doing that,
it's what you would expect from an
industry body, right? By doing that,
they end up with a small group of
companies and they miss a whole part of
the open-source ecosystem.
So, we focus on individuals, we bring
people together, we've become a sort of
convening point for the open tech
sector. We then do a bunch of research
and reporting, so we do legal and policy
work, we respond to legislation, we do
research into open tech in the UK and
beyond.
And then we do a bit of skills
development, we have the annual
conference that you've mentioned. We're
doing that a bit differently this year,
which we'll probably come back to. So we
really bring people together to talk
about the the stuff that's going on in
open tech.
>> Yeah, it really is a truly wonderful
organization. And of course And of
course your background is is also in the
kind of more on the on the legal and law
side, right? You've been 25 years legal
experience and you've done a lot of work
there with open source legal frameworks
as well as internet law.
>> Yeah, so I I guess I started in the mid
to late '90s as a lawyer, went through
the dot com boom. I actually thought
that that was going to be the pinnacle
of my tech career and I didn't think
there was going to be anything else
coming down the line that was going to
be quite as um
innovative and new and I really had
enjoyed that part of my career because
you're trying to fit the laws around the
technologies or make, you know, rather
than make the technology fit the law if
that makes sense.
So in 2008 when I joined Canonical, I
was just blown away at the stuff that
was going on and Canonical back then was
really cutting edge. I I can't really
comment so much on what they're doing
today. But it was really a moment in
time in the industry, so I've worked in
open source on and off since 2008.
And I thankfully I will say gave up
being a lawyer in what, 2018 19 and
started the role with OpenUK in 2019.
>> Amazing.
>> So in theory I still use my legal skills
in the work we do, but I don't have to
be a lawyer anymore.
>> Amazing. And so when OpenUK started, of
course it was probably we would say the
more traditional open source which we
think about open source maintainers
building software components that is
available for reuse under certain
licenses and so forth. Then AI happened
or as course AI's been happening for a
long time. AI hit mainstream and it
really caught everyone's attention
and Open UK has recently actually done a
lot in the in the world of AI as well.
Let's talk a little bit about what open
what openness means to AI and to LLMs.
When we think about an open model, which
has been thrown around a lot, what is an
open model?
>> Oh, you could get me into so much
trouble with that very small simple
question. There's been so much debate
about it and we've seen people trying to
come up with definitions. So, I'm going
to give you what I think this is all
about. And we all know what open source
software is, right? We spent 30 years
working on the open source definition,
working on licensing based on that,
relying on it as a a trust point. And
that trust point has allowed us to build
traction.
And for me, key to it is that anyone can
use the code for any purpose. Now, if we
take that
and sort of
bring it to the next level for AI, to me
it means that anyone can use what you're
giving them for any purpose. Now, you
can get into all the debates with models
and things about whether you have to
give the data, how much of it do you
have to give. My preference is that we
disaggregate the technology. We don't
try and define something that's so
emerging and that we look at AI as it
evolves. So, couple of years ago when
people were really trying to do
definitions, all they were thinking
about was language models. They weren't
thinking about agentic
or any of the stuff that's coming down
the line now, the robotics, whatever
else, embodiment. Um
so, I think the best way to view it is
to disaggregate the components, look at
what the components of the AI are and
ask the question about the components.
So, if we're looking at a model or an
algorithm, if we're looking at a data
set, if we're looking at an agent, is
that something that anybody can use for
any purpose? And that goes back to how
it's licensed. So, I would look at each
of the different components and then
whether or not it's on a an OSD
compliant license. So, the licenses that
you know from open source software like
the GPL, Apache, MIT, those kind of
things.
And if it is, then I would say that that
part of it is open source. It might not
be that the whole of the AI is, but that
part of it is.
>> And it's interesting when we say open
source cuz open source just means, you
know, the the the source code is there
for you to see.
Now, if I was to try and build an open
source component, a piece of software,
I could probably go ahead and well, it
would be open. I could probably build it
through through through GitHub, etc. And
some CICD pipeline. Uh with a model,
though, of course, just having the code
isn't really enough to be able to build
the model and use the model to the same
level. So, there are other there are
other kind of like terms that we've have
been thrown around here. Open model,
open weights, open training.
>> So, for me, I would say that you're
looking at the component part, which is
a recognizable part as the the
algorithm, the weight, the model as
being open and meeting that open source
standard. So, it's something that's
given to you freely in order that you
can use and reuse. It doesn't mean that
all the conditional parts are going to
be available. So, particularly when we
look at open weights and open models, I
think the real differentiator there is
that you're not getting the whole of the
LLM or S
small language model, whatever it is
that you're using, that you're only
getting that piece of it, the model
piece. You're not getting the data. And
that is almost universally the truth.
Not quite, but almost.
>> What's the value to the end user of
something being open source as a as a
model?
>> Yeah. I think it's enormous and I think
it depends on
where you're sitting in the ecosystem
and who the user is. Value depends very
much on who you are and where you are in
the ecosystem. And if we're looking at
innovators, that access to technology,
and when we saw the the first LLM's
being opened up in 2023, first of all
with the Llama leak and then Llama
opening up in the July, what we saw was
a pace of innovation that was really
unprecedented, right? And it was
suddenly giving the ecosystem the
access. And one of the big values of
something being open is a trait of the
development development, innovators
being able to freely access and use
technology they wouldn't otherwise have
access to and to build on top of it. And
you see that shift from Meta with Llama
through to Deep Seek with R1, you know,
and that wouldn't have happened one
without the other. So, you get that kind
of innovation. You also, when we look at
the landscape globally, we see two
dominant players, China and the US, way
ahead of everybody else. And then we
have the middle countries, there's about
10 of us together.
And really affording
what China and the US has built without
collaborative innovation would be
impossible. So, we really need access
either to what China and the US have
done, or we need access collaboratively
to further innovation to be able to just
fund the scale of the the cost of AI
innovation. And then for sort of end
users and individuals, it's again, it
comes back, as most things with open
source do, to cost benefits,
democratizing technology, allowing more
access, you know, in in India the AI
summit recently, we talked a lot about
access for all. And when you look at
something like the global south, the
only way they're ever going to get that
innovation is if we open it up and
create access.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it's actually a lot and a
lot of the the the things that you
mentioned there are also still very true
of traditional open source that you
mentioned with libraries and people
building upon that. It's a builder's
world, right? Um, so when we you
mentioned uh Meta and Llama there. Now
now Meta stated that Llama's open
source. The Linux Foundation backed them
up. You called them out.
>> Yeah, that was all a misunderstanding,
right?
>> The Linux Foundation didn't back them
up. So, it it all got very confused. So,
in July '23, we were actually Open UK
was the only organization that supported
the launch of Llama as open innovation.
>> Mhm.
>> And it was very carefully structured all
the way through, I think it was 23rd of
July off the top of my head, to that
date as open innovation because the
license has two things. It has an
acceptable use for policy that puts
restrictions in. And it has
a commercialization provision that says
when you hit X million users, you have
to go back and get a commercial license
from Meta.
>> Mhm.
>> Nobody knows what the the terms of that
license is cuz I don't think anybody's
hit that level of use that's been
trackable
>> Mhm.
>> to date. So, what that means is when you
go back to that basic principle of open
source that anyone can use it for any
purpose,
>> Right.
>> that just doesn't happen, right? You've
always got the risk of this restriction.
You don't have that same free flow, that
ability to cascade the outputs and let
somebody else use it, iterate it, and
build on top of it. So, that that's kind
of broken. And it was fine as open
innovation and we supported it, and I
still think it's the right thing to do
because that shift opening up an LLM was
critical for change in the industry.
>> Mhm.
>> And I think it will go down in history
as one of the seminal moments.
If you talk to people today about Llama
and Meta, they'll say to you that the
the word on the street is they're moving
away from openness.
>> Mhm.
>> And I think it's because they haven't
done it right. They haven't actually
created true open source.
>> Mhm.
>> So, they they themselves weren't calling
it until open source until Zuck posted
on Facebook. And by that point, you
know, nobody was going to go backwards
from there. Whether it was intentional
or not, we'll never know unless he tells
us, of course. Um but, you know, I
recently met Yann LeCun. I had a really
interesting conversation about some of
his aspirations and he thinks we should
be building a global model
across countries, across borders,
collaborating.
>> Mhm.
>> You know, and bringing money from states
together to do that. So, I suspect they
understood what open source was.
>> Mhm. Absolutely.
>> Yeah.
>> And for people who are building on
something that they believe is open
source, but actually it's not truly open
source in in to your definition,
what are the what are the real-world
risks that uh I as a developer might
have if I'm using something thinking
it's open source, but actually it's not?
>> Well, we get into uh something called
open washing which existed in open
source software before. To be quite
honest, it's such a nerdy thing that I
never thought it would be in the
mainstream. And there have been
headlines in the last couple of years in
the New York Times and The Economist
with open washing on the the cover of
the the magazines.
So, open washing is where somebody takes
that open source goodness and implies
that the deliverable they're sharing
with the world benefits from that open
source goodness when it doesn't really.
So, if you're Meta and you're saying
Llama is open source when it's not,
you're misleading people. It's
disingenuous at best. But, what it means
is you can't have the same reliance in
the ecosystem. So, you can't take, use,
recycle, know that you know, those
taking it from you can also use and
recycle.
And that becomes problematic, you know,
at at its simplest term. And I actually
think it's why Meta and now are looking
at shifting away. Because to get the
real value from open source, it goes way
beyond that legal definition of having a
license and making it, you know, open.
It goes to the heart of community and
collaboration and contribution.
And if people can't trust that openness
is going to be there forever. So, it's
like we we did a piece recently with one
of the creators of MCP, and he was
talking about why they've put MCP into
the Linux Foundation's new Agentech AI
Foundation. And it's all about keeping
it open and knowing that you've got that
security forever of it being open.
And I think that that's the bit that's
missing when you open wash, you take
away the trust. And if you don't have
trust, you will not be successful
because you don't have the ecosystem
around you and you won't grow that
ecosystem the way you would with real
open source.
>> Yeah, trust is a really important word
here as well. It's like it's it's it's
what
you know, when we talk about open source
and talk about the usages and the
sharing of of open source code and open
source models, trust is really what
binds the whole community together in in
terms of that. So, it's yeah, it's a
term that I think we really need to
think about when when talking when using
this this language. Um so, for for me as
a developer, if I'm using an open source
or if I'm using a model rather, how how
do I go about working deciding whether
this model is open source, how open it
is? Is there a good way easy way I can
do it? Mhm.
That's quite difficult one. So, I
suspect that if you're a developer doing
that, you're more technical than me, so
you understand the component parts of
the model better than I do. And you are
better placed than I am to to judge
which bits you need. Uh from a licensing
perspective, you want to make sure that
it's on one of the OSI approved OSD
compliant licenses that we all know, you
know, the GPLs, Apaches, MITs, something
that you've heard of and that that
hasn't been amended.
And that I think that's quite critical
to it. So, it's really understanding
what the licensing is
and then which bits you're getting and
you're not. Um
I think we really see a benefit from
documentation. And when we saw Deep Seek
releasing R1,
one of the things that really
differentiated it was that the data that
it was trained on wasn't provided. But
the documentation was so good that
within days Hugging Face had built R1
open, you know, and they're able to go
and train the same thing themselves cuz
they had that replicable data to help
them understand.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I think you're looking at what do I
need to use this if you're a developer.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
Let's talk about um
Well, actually one of the big rumors
more recently is about DeepSeek-4.
>> Right.
>> Uh when that's going to come, I don't
know. If that's going to come, I don't
know. But, um back in the day, a year
ago or so, when in fact I think I ran a
panel at State of Open Con
>> You did.
>> in and around DeepSeek with some of my
Chinese colleagues.
>> That's right. Yeah, and it was just as
DeepSeek came out, I think a couple of
weeks maybe after or a week after.
>> Um now, DeepSeek was a model that was I
think it's a distilled model from
>> Yeah, R1 open. R1 open R1 not R1 open,
yes.
>> Yeah, and and so first of all, what is a
distilled model?
>> Yeah, so they took Qwen and they took
Llama and used what was in there through
this distillation technique to create
something equivalent without actually
building a model from scratch. And that
was super impactful because it took the
price of building a model down
apparently to 5 million instead of 100
million, right? So, 5% of the the cost
at that point in time.
I think that that distillation was
really huge in terms of the innovation
for the time. But, we look at models
now, um India has just released through
Sarvam open models which are small
language models.
>> Mhm.
>> And it's quite interesting to see how
that progression has worked in the last
year. And that I think these small
language models, you know, that can be
used on phones and things that really
that's where we're shifting to as a
market.
>> Mhm. And it's interesting when people
are saying, "Oh, yeah, this is my
model." How you actually sometimes don't
even realize the models behind it. Um I
think uh I I I was reading a thread. It
was either on Hacker News or Reddit uh
this week just gone about uh the new uh
Cursor's is it the Composer-2 model or
something
>> Oh, I don't know. So, I had quite an
interesting experience in December. I
went out to China. I several years ago
now edited a book in on open source law.
And it's been translated by Chinese open
source community into Mandarin.
>> Mhm.
>> It's a 640-page long book. So, it took a
bit of time to do it. And I was really
lucky to get a call with DeepMind when I
was there. And I'm not allowed to
discuss the contents specifically,
but it was an interesting experience.
And it was interesting not just to talk
to them, but to talk to people across
the marketplace there.
And you know, like DeepMind is obviously
big, Quan and Kimmy, but Kimmy seemed to
be the thing that absolutely every
developer was using in China.
>> Interesting.
>> really seemed to be running ahead for
the developers.
>> And that's interesting with Kimmy
because there were rumors, I think, on
either Reddit or or Hacker News that
Kimmy was actually
the the core model behind Curses
Composer 2 model, which was just
recently released. And those are
I don't know if it was trolling. I don't
know if how much proof there is, but
it's very interesting that I think more
and more of developers are becoming uh
it's becoming it's becoming clearer to
developers that not every model is built
from scratch. And different models are
learning from each other. Absolutely.
>> Yeah, it has to be. It really has to be.
>> So, so what time do you think it makes
sense for a developer to use, you know,
an expensive model, maybe an Opus or
something from from OpenAI versus that,
you know, the cheaper model, you know,
these models that are derived from each
other because the costs are so low.
They're naturally going to be cheaper to
the end user. So, what stage does it
does it does a developer need to make
that decision?
>> I think we're in an odd position right
now where when we look at uptake and
adoption, it is actually much lower now
than you would expect it to be in the
open source front.
And it's very reminiscent of open source
software sort of 20 years ago. And I
think a lot of it is for similar
reasons, which were about risk
management, lack of understanding, you
know, maybe unnecessary fears, and not
really knowing what what the the
consequence of of it being open were
going to be. And I think what we saw
then was risk professionals, lawyers,
procurement, finance who had to sign off
on contracts saying no.
And then there was sort of a shift and a
momentum gathering around GitHub. And I
think what we will see, it won't be a
decision about a specific engineer
developer making a decision to use it,
is we'll see an industry shift where it
just becomes the norm. And I think it's
an absolute inevitability.
Um I'm reassured by hearing people like
Yann LeCun saying the same thing, you
know, at events I've been at in the last
few weeks. I I just think there is no
way around it, particularly for anybody
who is not from the US or China. And of
course, if you're from China, you're
already probably using open models.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Do do you feel like
there's a group, maybe it's a a startup
versus an enterprise or something? Do
you think there's like a a style of user
that is that finds open source models,
you know, get
>> I think there's a I think it depends on
where you are in the ecosystem. And
there's a lot of concern about IP,
managing your IP, leveraging your IP,
and making money, right? And I I think
you may be the wrong podcast to be
saying this,
but I think there is a piece where
there's no return on investment right
now, right? People are not seeing the
returns that they expect to get from AI
at this stage. And they're working out
how to actually use it in a practical
way when you get to that business level.
Um and I think we're a ways off people
being able to say, "Here is how AI is
working for me and here is how it's
saving me costs, taking away risk,
increasing my productivity."
So I think there's, you know, different
levels in that ecosystem. There's the
core creators, the sort of development
community, and then the end user.
And it's a gradual shift that we're
going to see. I don't think it's
particularly about anybody being the
right user for it. I think it's about
building understanding. I think there's
been a quality issue for a long time.
And we see that shifting now. I'm told
that there's very little difference in
the testing now. That you you're open
source models are getting to a point
where they are good enough.
>> And and there's probably like a a
variation in the accuracy that is needed
per task as well. Sometimes you might
want to do some prototyping or something
just to try think out an idea and and
actually get some rapid development.
It's not necessarily production code. In
that case, you know, I don't want a slow
model that's thinking very deeply.
>> Absolutely.
>> something that will create something
fast and cheaply for me.
>> Yeah. And that was one of the things I
took away from China, to be honest.
They're absolutely obsessed
with keeping everything lean and
reducing compute. All right, because
they don't have the same access that
others might have.
And I think we will increasingly,
particularly in this sort of world of
geopolitics, I think we will
increasingly see people being more and
more conservative about the access they
have to compute
and infrastructure. And looking at
what's most productive. And I think some
of the other models will start to come
into play then. I think there'll be a a
lot more
around these small language models and
opening up models, sharing more.
>> How much do you think an an an agent, an
AI agent, can plaster over some of the
uh
some of the problems that a cheaper
model, well not problems, but some of
the inefficiencies maybe that a cheaper
model will
will will will show that a more
expensive model would be able to just do
out of the box.
>> That's an interesting way of looking at
it. I think we're seeing such a shift to
agentic because it really starts to
deliver what we all thought AI was going
to give us, right?
It's a realer, more productive output
that you're getting by applying an agent
to what you're doing.
I suspect that that
is exactly as you're describing it. And
a sort of sticking plaster that will
hide a a multitude of sins with the
models and I hadn't really thought about
it like that before but yeah I think
probably right.
>> sometimes you have to ask a model a
hundred times to do something and it
gets it right once. An agent can share
that with me and I don't have to go
through the pain of the 99 problems.
>> No, but I've also been talking to people
recently about abstention and models
being trained not to respond when they
don't know the answer and it's not about
hallucination per se it's just about
some of the answers you get
from models because they want to always
please. And I think retraining them in
that way is quite important. So I think
we're seeing shifts there that will
actually be the quite critical for the
the business productivity of models and
the agentic layer on top of it.
I also speaking to people increasingly
see sectors looking at taking models and
refining those models for the sectors
and training it you know
Telco is one great example at Mobile
World Congress a couple of weeks ago the
GSMA one of their industry bodies has
pulled together all the big Telcos all
the network providers and they are
working collaboratively to train on
specific data related to Telco to refine
their models and you can imagine then
how your agent's going to work with
that. It's going to become super useful
and I think as that begins to sort of
bed in that's when we're going to really
start to see return on investment and
that's going to be critical to the
landscape.
>> Absolutely yeah.
We've talked about things like Lama.
Lama everyone has heard of Lama I
suspect. Is there is there a model that
you think an open source model that you
think oh do you know what this is a
really great model it does so much
but people aren't talking about it or
people just don't haven't heard of it
before.
>> I think Kimi is the the piece that we're
missing in the West just from the
reactions that I was seeing from
engineers from developers around me in
China you know it it's pace of of was so
fast and so great, that I think Kimmy's
probably being underutilized in the
west.
>> And tell us a bit about Kimmy.
>> So, Kimmy's Chinese open source model
created by Moonshot, which I think came
out towards the end of last year.
And
I've not used it, but I know that every
developer I spoke to said that it is
just the best.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I can only recommend it through word
of mouth and other people's
recommendations rather than my own.
>> Yeah, I know I've heard I've heard
actually quite similar. So, yeah, I've
heard it. It's funny how when It's like
a drumbeat, it's like
when Claude and and OpenAI were
originally kind of like bringing out
their models and everyone was saying,
"Oh, yeah, Claude's the best thing.
Claude's the best thing." And it's it's
all about word of mouth a lot of the
time, isn't it?
>> Well, this is the thing that people
don't understand. So, when you are in
that open ecosystem, or even an
ecosystem, it's about community, right?
And I think within engineering over the
last 20, 30 years, it's something that's
been refined so that it's now a dark art
understand how to build community, how
to get contribution, how to engage
people, how to keep them engaged, how to
be there for maintainers. You know, that
stuff, if you're not from an open
background, you don't understand it. You
think you're going to build something
and they will just come. You don't
understand that you need to have a user
base and people start and that that's
sort of, you know, uh drum signals that
everybody hears and everybody suddenly
around. I mean, Maltbook.
>> Mhm.
>> How quickly did you know about it? Cuz I
was sitting by Saturday trying to get
myself all into it, you know? It's just
one of those things that our whole
ecosystem converses,
whether it's through social media,
whether it's through, you know, sharing
tools amongst each other, but that there
was a very definite way that it happens.
And I think that art of collaboration is
something that we're going to see more
and more.
>> Mhm. Uh you know, there's a significant
number of open source options for people
to to pick from. Why are most developers
still defaulting to closed model APIs as
their as their go-to?
>> It's interesting. I think that's
shifting. And when you say closed model
APIs, do you mean closed models or
closed model API? And if they even if
they're using a closed model API,
they're probably using MCP
>> Mhm.
>> as a protocol, which is open to get
there.
>> That's a great question, actually. So,
explain the difference there between a
a closed model, a non-open source model,
>> Yeah.
>> a closed model API,
the same. It's whether or not they the
API is open or closed, and whether it's
something that's freely available.
Generally, you will get an open API
because somebody wants to build an
interface that everybody is able to
access.
>> Mhm.
>> And then when we look at MCP, model
context protocol, you have a an open
standard effectively,
>> Mhm.
>> which hasn't gone through a standards
process. It's a de facto standard like
so many things in open tech. And it's
just become the thing that everybody
uses because it does what they needed to
do, and it joins things up. It joins up
between the old and the new world, and
the new world and the new world. But,
all of that being open means that in
that ecosystem, even if you're going
from a closed model to a closed API,
you're still using something that's open
in the middle.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Very interesting.
Let's switch a little bit from models
>> Yeah.
>> to agents. We've touched on agents
briefly.
>> Hey everyone. Hope you're enjoying the
episode so far. Our team is working
really hard behind the scenes to bring
you the best guests so we can have the
most informative conversations about
agentic development. Whether that's
talking about the latest tools, the most
efficient workflows, or defining best
practices. But, for whatever reason,
many of you have yet to subscribe to the
channel. If you're enjoying the podcast
and want us to continue to bring you the
very best content, please do us a favor
and hit that subscribe button. It really
does make a difference and lets us
continue to improve the quality of our
guests and build an even better product
for you. All right, back to the episode.
How important is it that if someone uses
a an open model?
>> Mhm.
>> They then use an open agent as well.
>> I think all of this really comes down to
personal preference and choice, right?
I'm going to advocate for you doing it
openly because I think that you are
going to build community around it.
You're going to build adoption and
engagement, and you are able to take
technology innovation
and iterate yourself on it and share it
with others, right? So, I think if you
open that up, you're going to build an
ecosystem that you're not going to build
otherwise, and that's important to most
people. But it is like the the
conversation we're having before. It
really comes down to my IP and whether
people feel that the only way they're
going to be able to monetize, if that's
their goal,
is to to hold on to the IP and keep it
closed. You go back to 2023, and there
was a famous leaked memo from Google in
May 23. It is only the opinion of one
person. I have to caveat it with that.
And it says, "We have no moat." And what
they meant was the the moat the water
around the castle, which is normally
intellectual property, which will hold
something safe, which will keep
everybody off, allow you to charge
revenue, that that just wasn't there
once things started to open up. And I
think that's going to be the case with
most things in AI. I I suspect we're
going to see it really open up. Partly
because we're learning from history,
right? We've ended up with eight
companies. I think eight's right. Um who
control the digital infrastructure. And
I don't think anybody wants to see that
as the AI future with eight companies
controlling our AI future. So, the value
of opening things up is something that
is much more understood now than it was
30 years ago when we began those big
tech journeys.
>> Yeah. So, looking forward now, let's
let's let's get the crystal ball out and
start start gazing into into what we
think is going to happen. Um what would
what would you love to see going forward
in either maybe adoption but more the
the the the innovation around
open source and AI?
>> I'm probably not going to give you the
answer you're expecting.
>> Go for it.
>> So, about eight years ago China was very
clear that it was adopting an open
source first strategy as a nation.
And that was embedded into policy. And
then very specific activities and
actions were taken across the ecosystem
by the Chinese government, Chinese
enterprises.
And I think if you want to have a
successful open source AI
ecosystem future, if you want to be able
to compete with what China's achieved on
the open source front and AI, I think
you really have to look at that
ecosystem and landscape and what we
need. I don't know if you saw it, but
about three, four weeks ago Kanishka
Narayanan, who's the UK's AI minister,
made a sweeping statement, which I'm
very pleased with, but it's quite
sweeping, that the UK is going to become
the home of open source AI.
>> Mhm.
>> So, how is he going to do that? How are
we going to make that happen? And I
think we have to learn lessons from
China. We have to build on what they've
done and do something more. We have to
look at what everybody else is currently
doing and how the world has changed in
that eight-year period. And I think for
me, putting those pieces of the picture
in place, so it involves things like
capacity and skills development and open
source. It involves things like building
a national foundation.
And I think we need a body that could
hold something as standard like MCP,
that could hold a gentic or
you know, language model technology
on behalf of UK enterprises.
>> Mhm.
>> And I think that's going to be a big
shift and I'm hoping that we will move
towards that. But I think that model is
something we're going to see in every
country. There was a a press piece this
week that described the Linux Foundation
as if it was the US National Foundation.
>> Mhm.
>> But we've all been contributing to that,
right? And it was talking about a land
grab around how the US is trying to own
the standards in AI. You know, China
will be doing the same thing. For us to
do it, we need the home of that.
And I think we'll also see other
countries like Germany and France doing
something similar. They've both taken
steps in that direction without fully
doing it already.
So, I think building the the environment
for a successful ecosystem at a national
level
for me is the the missing magic piece.
That's what I'd like to see us do.
>> And I think, you know, we were alluding
to it during the episode,
models getting better,
people adopting it more. Is there
anything in the way, do you think, in
future for people to really grab hold of
open-source models and use it, you know,
in in whether it's in production or or
more aggressively than they are today?
Or do you think it's just a a timing
thing that it will happen?
>> I think it will happen. I think it's
inevitable.
I think what's in the way of it is,
again, going back to 20 years ago in
software, it's understanding
and the people who are able to stop that
happening. The sort of naysayers, those
with concerns, who maybe don't
understand the risks associated.
I think there's that piece where there
are various blockers. You know, you
probably saw about a year ago, I think
it was, JP Morgan's CIO saying that my
supply chain isn't user agentic. You
know, so that there are pieces like that
that will shift over time as we get more
confident.
And I think we probably have had so much
press in the last 30 months around AI
that has caused a lot of concerns for a
lot of people. I mean, things like
mobile would terrify people. You know,
if you explain to somebody who's not in
tech that you've now got social media
for agents and they're off creating
their own religion, they think that's
how, right? You know, and you can
understand why. So, I think there has to
be a sort of shift in general skills,
general understanding. People are scared
they're going to lose their jobs, so
they're resistant to it. And I I think
we have to look at the future of
society, the future of work, and the
impacts that AI can
maybe will have,
but it's perhaps not as quick as people
are panicking around, and also building
that understanding and giving them the
training that they need.
>> Yeah, amazing. And let's pivot slightly
onto back onto Open UK. Um what can
people look forward to uh a in the next
year with
>> There's a lot going on.
Yeah, so we've got ongoing reporting. We
did our first international reports at
the end of last year with India, because
we were there for the AI Impact Summit
in February. We did quite a few events
there.
So, we've got an Africa report coming
out this week. Um we are working with
the Chinese open-source ecosystem to
build one in China as well, particularly
focused on not just open-source, but AI.
We have a bunch of reports. We'll do our
annual report, all the bits and pieces
that you're used to seeing from us.
We have a a number of events in
Parliament.
We just had one last week with the
Conservative Opposition Ministers
talking to them about the the needs of
open source.
I think you'll see a lot more
conversation around sovereignty.
We have taken State of Open, which is
our annual conference that I know you
know well, but we've taken it on the
road this year. So, we've got confirmed
dates now. I think 5th of June in
Edinburgh at NatWest offices, and then
8th of July in Cambridge at Pembroke
College. We'll do probably three more of
those in the autumn, and then we've got
our awards launching after Easter.
Great opportunity to nominate someone
you know, or yourself even, for an
award. I think we've got about 10, 12
categories this year.
And that will take place at the House of
Commons on the 5th of November.
>> Amazing. And you actually
>> You didn't pick up on that. It will take
place at the House of Commons on the 5th
of November.
>> of November.
>> 5th of November. Yeah, Guy Fawkes.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> So, for anybody who's not from the UK or
hasn't done their UK history. 5th of
November is a night upon which many
years ago a gentleman called Guy Fawkes
tried to blow up the House of Commons,
which we're going to on its anniversary.
>> Amanda, it's been an absolute pleasure
and and and sorry it was so long. We
should have we should have done this
earlier, but it was worth the wait.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you very much, Amanda, and all the
best with OpenUK. And and for people who
want to learn more about OpenUK, what's
the what's the best place?
>> So, uh website openuk.uk,
stateofopencon.com
for the conference, and then LinkedIn is
generally where we hang out. Although,
as we were saying, maybe we need to do
more on X.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Yeah. Do check that
out. That's uh a really great community,
very very welcoming community, and
actually very up-to-date with a lot of
what's happening. I love the reports.
There was a really interesting one
uh that that I actually saw in the
Houses of Commons or House of Lords, I
think it was, uh with DORA, uh the DORA
uh and and OpenUK report, which was
which was excellent. So, thanks for
tuning in, and we'll see you on the next
episode. Bye for now.